Joseph Floch Papers
Joseph Floch Papers
1935-1960
Floch, Joseph, 1895-1977.
0.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American painter. Born in Vienna, Austria. Exhibition catalogs (1947-1960); published material about Floch in French and German, 1935 and 1955; and two undated biographical sheets.
148982
Biographical History
Joseph Floch (1895-1977) was an Austrian-American artist known for his modernist landscape and figure paintings. Born in Vienna, Austria on November 5, 1895, he studied at the State Academy of Fine Arts in Vienna (1913-1919) and then in 1926 moved to Paris, where the art dealer B. Weill became his patron. In 1941 he emigrated to New York and ten years later became an American citizen. In 1962 he joined the faculty of the New School of Research.
Floch was an Academician of the National Academy of Design, a member of the Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors, the American Federation of the Arts and the Salon d'Automne in Paris, France. He received numerous awards and prizes in his career as an artist, including one from the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, (1944); the National Institute of Arts and Letters in 1955, the International Exhibition in Paris in 1937 and the National Academy of Design in 1960.
Mr. Floch's work is in the permanent collections of museums around the world, including the Museum of Modern Art, the Whitney Museum of American Art, the de Young Memorial Museum in San Francisco, the Museum of Modern Art and various museums in France and Tel Aviv and Jerusalem. His work has been exhibited at major museums in the United States and Europe, including the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, the Whitney Museum of American Art, the Art Institute of Chicago, the Carnegie Institute, the New York World's Fair, and the Paris Salon.
Mr. Floch was also a contributor of articles and reproductions to many newspapers throughout the United States and Europe.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Joseph Floch Papers consists of biographical material, subject file, and published material.
Biographical material consists of two sheets of biographical data. Subject files contains exhibition catalogues of various showings of Floch's work. Published material consists of two books about Floch, one in German and one in French, and two magazine articles about Floch, in French.
Arrangement of the Collection
Subject files' exhibit catalogs are arranged alphabetically by gallery name. Published material is subdivided by type and arranged alphabetically by title.
Related Material
has the papers of a number of American artists. Please see for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Floch, Joseph, 1895-1977.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Artists -- United States.; Austrian Americans.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Clippings (information artifacts); Exhibition catalogs.; Artists.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Two sheets (Box 1)
- Exhibition catalogs
  - Associated American Artists Galleries, 1947; 1949 (Box 1)
  - M.H. de Young Memorial Museum, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Galerie Drouant-David, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Maxwell Galleries, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Garelick's Gallery, undated (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 1)
- Published material
  - Books about
    - Joseph Floch (in French), 1951 (Box 1)
    - Die Kunst und das Schöneheim (in German), 1955 (Box 1)
  - Magazine articles about
    - "L'Art et Les Artistes", 1935 (Box 1)
    - "Prisme des Arts", undated (Box 1)